Guide to the Milo Parker Jewett Papers, 1828-1913 (bulk 1856-1882)
Archives and Special Collections Library, Vassar College Libraries
Milo Parker Jewett Papers
1828-1913
1856-1882
Jewett, Milo P.
1.1 cubic feet (4 boxes)
Archives and Special Collections Library, Vassar College Libraries
Papers related to Jewett's involvement with the founding of Vassar College and its early operation, as well as biographical and Jewett family materials
Biographical Note
Milo P. Jewett, first president of Vassar College, was born in St. Johnsbury, VT in 1801. He attended Dartmouth College and Andover Theological Seminary. In 1839 he founded the Judson Female Institute in Alabama, which was known as one of the best schools for women in the ante-bellum south. A few years later he was ordained in the Baptist ministry, having changed his views on baptism. In 1855 Jewett purchased the Cottage Hill Seminary in Poughkeepsie. There he met Matthew Vassar and is credited with suggesting to Vassar that he use his fortune to establish a women's college. Jewett was one of the original trustees of Vassar College and was elected president in 1861. Disagreements with other board memebers and ultimately with Matthew Vassar forced Jewett's resignation in 1864. In spite of his short tenure he did much to shape the early years of the college, arranging for the purchase of land and the construction of buildings which still serve the college. In 1867 Jewett moved to Milwaukee, where he lived out the rest of his life as an active participant in educational, philanthropic, and religious affairs. Jewett died in 1882.
Note: Additional biographical information is available in the Vassariana Biographical File.
Scope and Content Note
Papers primarily concern women's education and Vassar College and include his letters to Matthew Vassar, Nathan Bishop, Martin B. Anderson, and others relating to the proposed female college, staff and teaching appointments, his resignation, and other college affairs, 1856-1864; letters and essays from educators in response to Jewett's circular letter about the organization of Vassar Female College, 1861-1863; Jewett's essays and statements on the organization and curriculum for Vassar Female College, 1856-1864; other letters received on college business, his essay on Vassar College, and the benefits of teaching applied science (cooking), 1861-1880; his report on a trip to Europe, 1863; photocopy and typescript of his Origin of Vassar; obituaries of Jewett, 1882, and his wife, 1889; a Vassar family letter, 1828; and letters to James Monroe Taylor about Jewett, 1888-1913.
Access
This collection is open for research according to the
regulations of the Vassar College Archives and Special Collections Library
without any additional restrictions.
Related Materials
See also the Benson J. Lossing Papers as well as the Sarah J. Hale Papers, Vassar College Library
Subject Headings
Names:
Vassar, Matthew, 1792-1868; Bishop, Nathan, 1808-1880; Anderson, Martin B.; Taylor, James Monroe, 1848-1916; Vassar family
Organizations:
Vassar College--Presidents; Vassar College--Employees; Vassar College--Faculty; Vassar Female College
Subjects:
Family--New York (State)--Poughkeepsie; Women's colleges--New York (State)--Poughkeepsie; Women--Education; Cookery--Study and teaching; College presidents
Places:
Europe--Description and travel
VCL Categories
Vassar College Presidents
Encoding Information
Encoded by Elizabeth Clarke, May 2007.
Acquisition Information
Gift of various donors and purchase.
Location of Originals
Some originals are located at University of Rochester and at Dartmouth College.
Container List
- Letters to Matthew Vassar, Nathan Bishop, and others, 1856-1882; (15 letters) (Folder 1.1)
- Positive photocopies of 10 Jewett letters to Martin B. Anderson, from the University of Rochester Library, 1861-1866; (10 photocopies) (Folder 1.2)
- Letters to Jewett, (7 letters) (Folder 1.3)
- Manuscript documents by Jewett with related correspondence. (Folder 1.4)
- Publications: Vassar Female College: Report on Organization, 1863 (Folder 1.5)
- Publications: Vassar Female College: The President's Visit to Europe, 1863 (Folder 1.5)
- Publications: In Memoriam: Milo Parker Jewett, 1882 (Folder 1.5)
- Correspondence with James Monroe Taylor relating to Jewett, 1888-1913; (6 letters) (Folder 2.1)
- Photocopies of materials relating to Jewett, 1828-1882 (Folders 2.2-2.3)
- Photocopies of Jewett materials in Dartmouth College Archives. (Folder 2.4)
- Handwritten copies of Jewett's manuscript, Origin of Vassar College. (Box 3)
- Handwritten copy of Jewett’s manuscript, Origin of Vassar College, originally given to Mrs. Mary Jameson and bound with a copy of Catalogue of the Trustees, Officers and Students of the Judson Female Institute: Marion, Perry County, Alabama (Marion, AL, 1855) and Memorial of Milo Parker Jewett, LL.D. (Milwaukee, 1882), as well as several letters providing the provenance of the bound manuscript. (Folder 4.1)
- Typescript of Origin of Vassar College, (in binder) (Folder 4.2)
- Miscellaneous negative photostatic copies (Folder 4.3-4.4)